Guide to the Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus records 2017.011
Brooklyn Historical Society
Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus records
1906-2017
2002-2017
Brooklyn Historical Society
Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus
2017.011
16 Linear Feet in 10 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, 3 flat file folders.
The collection consists of records and research materials created and collected by the Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus (FROGG), a community-based organization founded in 2002. The materials document the organization's efforts combatting rezoning and overdevelopment, restoring the habitat and water quality of the Gowanus Canal, and preserving the industrial heritage of Greater Gowanus. The collection comprises administrative records, project files, reports, correspondence, research files, newspaper clippings, magazines, photographs, audiovisual materials, maps, protest signs, posters and ephemera. The records were collected and donated by FROGG's archivist, Linda Mariano (1943-2021). The materials in the collection date from 1906 to 2017, with the bulk of the materials being created and collected between 2002 and 2017.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of records created by Linda Mariano and the Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus (FROGG). The materials in the collection document the organization's activities combatting rezoning and overdevelopment, restoring the environment and water quality of the Gowanus Canal, and preserving the industrial heritage of Greater Gowanus. The collection comprises administrative records, project files, reports, correspondence, newspaper clippings, magazines, research materials, photographs, audiovisual media, maps, protest signs, posters and ephemera. The materials in the collection date from 1906 through 2017, with the bulk of the materials being created and collected between 2002 and 2017.
Series 1: Administrative records consists of materials related to the administrative duties of the organization, including by-laws, meeting notes, meeting agendas, membership information, resumes and biographies of the group's board of directors.
Series 2: Project files includes applications, plans, reports, press releases, manuals and planning documents for FROGG-related projects, programs, and appeals. Sub-series 2.1: Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus projects and grants comprise records documenting FROGG projects and programs implemented between 2003 and 2015, including the Gowanus Brownfield Cleanup Program, Gowanus Canal National Priority Listing, Gowanus Canal Superfund designation, and a Technical Assistance Grant. Sub-series 2.2: Environmental and historical reports include assessments, surveys, sampling data, and reports on environmental hazards and the historical significance of the Gowanus Canal corridor from 1977 to 2016. Documents in this series were used for research in support of the group's advocacy and activism for designating the Gowanus Canal as a Superfund site and protected urban industrial district. This series also includes plans for environmental restoration and wetland creation from the United States Army Corps of Engineers, the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, the New York City Department of Environmental Protection, and the Environmental Protection Agency(EPA). Sub-series 2.3: Development plans and appeals compiles plans for development and rezoning in Greater Gowanus neighborhoods including plans for residential buildings, bridge repairs, industrial improvements, and waterfront access. The series also consists of appeals made to the Board of Standards and Appeals against the development and rezoning of the Gowanus Canal corridor from mixed industrial use to residential.
Series 3: Correspondence comprises letters, notes, and research material exchanged between FROGG members and concerned citizens, community groups, lawyers, urban planners, elected officials and government agencies. The series includes written responses to various development and rezoning projects in Gowanus, including proposals for Gowanus Village, Atlantic Yards, Whole Foods and 363-365 Bond Street.
Series 4: Subject files contain research and reference material about subjects, people, and organizations related to FROGG's mission and advocacy campaigns. Subjects include brownfields, emergency preparedness, historic preservation, land use law, tidal wetlands and toxics targeting.
Series 5: Clippings and magazines document press relating to FROGG programs and activities, as well as research and reference material on diverse topics and current events covering Gowanus, Red Hook, and Caroll Gardens from 1973 to 2017. Topics cover culture and arts events, urban farming, development and rezoning, housing, pollution, land use, landmarking, parks and green spaces, superfund designation and cleanup. While most of the clippings encompass matters local to Greater Gowanus, FROGG's Archivist also collected national coverage of environmental issues, flooding, gentrification, global warming, historical preservation, Hurricane Sandy and zoning.
Series 6: Photographs and audiovisual media consists of photographic prints, negatives, slides, and moving images from 1999-2015 documenting architecture, pollution, wildlife, flooding, construction, activism and cultural activities in Gowanus. Most of the photographs were taken by Linda Mariano along the Gowanus Canal, additional photographers include Arthur Mortensen, David Schlegel, and members of the Urban Divers Estuary Conservancy. Videos in the collection include short documentary films about Gowanus, highlighting community organizations, cultural performances, interviews with community members and the EPA Superfund designation.
Series 7: Printed materials and ephemera comprise posters, protest signs, postcards, newsletters, press releases, pamphlets, flyers, maps, books and pins produced by FROGG, other community organizations, cultural institutions and artists located in Greater Gowanus. Posters, protest signs, flyers and pins document FROGG's activism against overdevelopment and in support of the EPA Superfund designation. Reproductions of maps showcase the industrial heritage of Gowanus and the evolving urban and natural environments.
Existence and Location of Copies
Copies of the following published materials are also included in the Center for Brooklyn History Library's Main Collection:
- The Best of Brooklyn: a borough of manufacturers (382.1025 B)
- Eco-Gowanus: urban remediation by design (307.3416 E)
- Lavender Lake: Brooklyn's Gowanus Canal (VIDEO 628.168 L)
- Woodlands, wetlands, and wildlife: a guide to the natural areas of New York City parks (574.5264 W)
Biographical
Linda Mariano (1943–2021) was a painter, author, art teacher, activist and co-founder of the Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus. Linda attended New York University and graduated with a B.S. in Art Education in 1964. In 1967, she received an M.F.A. in Painting from Brooklyn College. Linda moved from the West Village to Gowanus in 1976 with her husband Joseph Mariano and their daughter Rachel (b. 1972). Linda was a published author and art instructor. Her published works include "The Encyclopedia of Knitting and Crochet Stitch Patterns"(1977) and "Romantic Embroidery: Floral Designs and Motifs" (1984).
Linda became involved in Gowanus activism in 2002 when she received a notice from a developer that wanted to demolish an old industrial building at 450-460 Union Street and replace it with luxury condominiums. Linda mobilized with Greater Gowanus residents to fight rezoning and development, co-founding the Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus. She became the group's archivist, collecting and maintaining all materials such as meeting agendas, attendance records, minutes, copies of grant proposals and applications, newspaper and magazine articles, photographs and historical documents related to Gowanus. Linda continued to work with FROGG and supported the environmental restoration and historic preservation of Gowanus up until her death in April 2021.
Historical Note
The Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus (FROGG) is a grassroots community organization founded between 2002 and 2004 by Linda Mariano, Bette Stoltz, Margaret Maugenest, Mauren Donnelly and a group of citizens concerned with the historic preservation of Greater Gowanus and environmental restoration of the Gowanus Canal corridor.
The group first came together in 2002 to oppose the demolition of The Green Building at 450-460 Union Street, a former brass foundry built in 1889. A developer planned to demolish the building and replace it with luxury condominiums. Community members mobilized to protest the demolition and rezoning of the building to the Board of Standards and Appeals (BSA). After two years of discussions, the BSA denied the developer's plans for residential rezoning and saved the building from demolition. As a result of the BSA determination in 2004, Linda Mariano and residents from Gowanus, Carroll Gardens and Red Hook formalized the group under the name the Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus. The group dedicated its efforts to combatting rezoning and overdevelopment, restoring the environment and water quality of the Gowanus Canal, and preserving the industrial heritage of Greater Gowanus.
The group continued to fight spot rezoning happening throughout Gowanus, transforming formerly industrial areas into residential neighborhoods. Their arguments were for both the preservation of the industrial heritage of the area, as well as promoting the cleanup of centuries of pollution into and along the Gowanus Canal to create a healthier and safer Gowanus Canal corridor for current and future residents. The group protested that the city and developers conduct public reviews, environmental assessments, and environmental impact statements before plans and rezoning receive approval. FROGG responded to development plans for Gowanus Village (2003-2005), Whole Foods (2005-2007), Atlantic Yards (2009), and twice protested 363-365 Bond Street, once in 2007 against the Toll Brothers and again in 2012 against the Lightstone Group.
In 2006 and 2008, FROGG joined with other local like-minded organizations to discuss environmental priorities for the Canal and address the government's role in the cleanup efforts. Collaborators included the Gowanus Canal Conservancy, Gowanus Canal Community Development Corporation, and the Urban Divers Estuary Conservancy, among others. The discussions featured representatives from the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, the New York City Department of Environmental Preservation, the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC), and the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). It was unclear whose jurisdiction the Canal cleanup fell under, causing any remediation or restoration efforts to be delayed. In December 2008, DEC Commissioner Peter Grannis sent a letter to the EPA and asked them to evaluate the Gowanus Canal as a potential federal Superfund site. FROGG mobilized to support the Superfund designation and organized demonstrations, produced informational materials to educate community members and recruited signatures for a community petition. In March 2010, the EPA placed the Gowanus Canal on the National Priorities List of Superfund Sites, assigning the cleanup duties to the federal government and the fiscal responsibility to the industrial and municipal polluters.
FROGG continues to work with the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission, the Historic Districts Council, and the New York State Historic Preservation Office to pursue the historic designation of the Gowanus Corridor as an Urban Industrial District. The designation would preserve landmarks for future generations, maintain existing structures and open spaces for adaptive reuse and protect the Gowanus Canal Corridor from overdevelopment. As a member of the Gowanus Landmarks Coalition, FROGG helped to get five important Gowanus buildings landmarked by New York City in 2019.
Over 20 years, FROGG programs and activities included community planning, implementing a brownfield cleanup program, creating the Gowanus Canal Community Advisory Group, collaborating with urban planners, and conducting environmental, historical and cultural tours of Gowanus. FROGG's projects were supported by grants from the Citizens Committee for New York City (2003, 2006 and 2009), the Brooklyn Historical Society (2008), and the Environmental Protection Agency (2012), among others. The organization is still active as of 2022.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series, including three sub-series.
Series 1: Administrative records is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Series 2: Project files is arranged into three sub-series including Sub-series 2.1: Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus projects and grants, Sub-series 2.2: Environmental and historical reports, and Sub-series 2.3: Development plans and appeals. The sub-series are arranged alphabetically by folder or publication title.
Series 3: Correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
Series 4: Subject files is arranged alphabetically.
Series 5: Clippings and magazines is arranged alphabetically.
Series 6: Photographs and audiovisual media is arranged alphabetically by folder and publication title.
Series 7: Printed materials and ephemera is arranged alphabetically by folder and publication title.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Linda Mariano, 2017.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Additional equipment is required to view or access material stored on CDs, DVDs, VHS, and two cassettes.
Separated Materials
Oversized maps and architectural drawings are in the Othmer Library print room flat file as indicated in the container location.
Community organizing |z New York (State) |z New York; Superfund sites; Historic preservation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Pollution |z New York (State) |z New York; Gowanus Canal (New York, N.Y.); New York Harbor (N.Y. and N.J.); Gowanus (New York, N.Y.); Administrative records; Newsletters; Correspondence; Reports; Documentary-style films; Color prints (photographs); Photographs; Activism; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clippings (information artifacts); Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Series 1: Administrative records
  - Board of directors, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-laws, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Community board 6, 2003-2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Linda Mariano consignment forms, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Linda Mariano resume, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meeting notes, 2004-2009 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership, circa 2002-2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pace University law clinic, 2004-2013 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Project files
  - Sub-series 2.1: Friends and Residents of Greater Gowanus projects and grants
    - Community planning, 2013-2014 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Community Preservation Trust planning document, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Department of Environmental Protection stakeholders related materials, 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Gowanus Brownfield Cleanup Program, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Gowanus Brownfield Opportunity Area applications, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Gowanus Brownfield Opportunity Area request for proposals, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Gowanus Canal Community Advisory Group, 2010-2013 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Gowanus Canal Community Development Corp. grants and projects, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Gowanus Canal Conservancy, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Gowanus Canal National Priority List listing support document, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Gowanus Canal superfund designation press releases, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Landmarks Preservation Commission, 2005-2016 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - National Register of Historic Places, 2005-2010 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - [Superfund Community Involvement Handbook], 2002 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Technical Assistance Grant agreement and related materials, 2012-2015 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Technical Assistance Grant application, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - Technical Assistance Grant technical advisor proposals, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Preserve New York grant program check, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series 2.2: Environmental and historical reports
    - Department of Environmental Conservation brownfield information, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Department of Environmental Protection long term control plan, 2004-2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Environmental assessment statement, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - [Final report on water quality and biological improvements after reactivation of the Gowanus Canal Flushing Tunnel], 2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Gowanus Bay and Canal Feasibility Study Milestone Report, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - [Gowanus Bay and Canal Fish and Epibenthic Invertebrate Sampling Program], 2004 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Gowanus Bay and Canal Hydrology, Hydraulics, Hydrodynamic and Water Quality Appendix, circa 2001-2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Gowanus Bay and Canal Project Management Plan, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Gowanus Canal and Bay Ecosystem Restoration Project Upland Site Assessment, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - [Gowanus Canal Benthic Sampling Data Documentation], 2003 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Gowanus Canal contaminants, 1990-2010 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Gowanus Canal Corridor Historic Preservation Studio, Columbia University, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Gowanus Canal Corridor Rezoning and Related Actions, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Gowanus Canal Development Study, 1987-2004 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - [Gowanus Canal Local Area Tributary Study, City of New York], 1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Gowanus Canal public health assessment community fact sheet, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Gowanus Canal waterbody/watershed data compilation, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Gowanus Canal waterbody/watershed facility plan report, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - [Gowanus Canal watershed impact of development of Atlantic Yards], 2004-2007 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - [Gowanus facilities upgrade], 2006-2010 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - [Gowanus neighborhood analysis final report], 2008 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - [Gowanus Study Area Data Assessment Report], 2003 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Hazard Ranking System Documentation Package, Gowanus Canal, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 23-25, Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Hudson-Raritan Estuary Comprehensive Restoration Plan, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - National Register of Historic Places evaluation and assessment of the Gowanus Canal, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - New York City Industrial Policy, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - New York City Open Industrial Uses Study, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - New York City's Wastewater Treatment System, circa 2005-2008 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Preserving Place and Production, Gowanus Works, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Property and pollution assessments, 1995-2013 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - [Red Hook and Gowanus community challenges and development], 2016 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - [Sediment Quality Evaluation Report], 2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - [Sediment Sampling Work Plan], 2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Army Corps of Engineers Gowanus Canal wetlands creations reports, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Wetland creation general investigation report, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sub-series 2.3: Development plans and appeals
    - 130 3rd Street, 409 Bond Street plans, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 255 Butler Street, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - 363-365 Bond Street, 2008-2012 (Box 4, Folder 18-21)
    - 460 Union Street, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - 460 Union Street architectural plans, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Architectural plans, 2005-2011 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Board of Standards and Appeals 460 Union Street, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Board of Standards and Appeals 460 Union Street testimony, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Board of Standards and Appeals hearing forms, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Combined sewer overflows, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Department of Buildings application data, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Department of City Planning waterfront zoning provisions, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Gowanus, A Strategy for Industrial Retention, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - [Green-wood Cemetery Battle Hill View Corridor plan], 2010 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - [New York City waterfront access plans], circa 2002-2015 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - New York University urban planning program, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - [Plan for the improvement of the Gowanus Canal], 1906 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - [Preliminary plans for Third Street bridge over Gowanus Canal], 1979 (Folder Flat File 1)
    - [Protecting and Growing New York City's Industrial Job Base], 2005 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Public place site, 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Red Hook's waterfront access plan, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Remedial work plan 2nd Street site, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
    - Third Street bridge repair plan, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Toll Brothers brownfield application, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - [Zoning resolution, residents district regulations], 2004 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Series 3: Correspondence
  - Brad Lander letter, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Carroll Street Station, 1996-1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Complaints against a lawyer, 2014 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2005 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2006-2008 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2009-2010 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2011-2017 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Ernest Migliaccio, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - FROGG letter to Community Board 6, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Gowanus Alliance, 2014 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Gowanus Canal Community Advisory Group, 2010-2013 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Gowanus Canal superfund designation, 2004-2010 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - Gowanus rezoning, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Gowanus Village brownfield site, 2003-2005 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
  - Grady Southard, Brooklyn Law, 2012-2013 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Historic District Council, 2010-2015 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Hudson Raritan estuary, 2009-2010 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Land use committee of Community Board 6, 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Letters to Environmental Protection Agency, Army Corps, and Department of Environmental Protection, 2003-2014 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Notes, 2007-2011 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Resisting reality [response to Atlantic Yards project], 2009 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Response to 363-365 Bond Street project, Toll Brothers, 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Response to 363-365 Bond Street project, The Lightstone Group, 2012-2014 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Superfund designation opposition, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Trust for Public Land, 2009-2012 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Whole Foods Market brownfield site, 2005-2007 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - With regards to Whole Foods, 2009-2012 (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
- Series 4: Subject files
  - Alex Matthiessen, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Battlefield grants, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Brownfields, 2005-2009 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Center for an Urban Future, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Community Environmental Legal Defense Fund, 2013-2014 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - [Emergency preparedness], 2007-2012 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - [Environmental organizations], 1997-2009 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Federal Emergency Management Agency, 2009-2013 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Gowanus businesses, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Historic preservation, 2005-2009 (Box 7, Folder 19)